Finding Aid for Frederick E. Moncrieff papers, 1947-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frederick E. Moncrieff papers 1947-2000 1961
Moncrieff, Frederick E.
93268 Aa2
Frederick Moncrieff worked as an editor, writer, photographer, and manager for the University of Michigan News and Information Services between 1946 and 1966. He accompanied the University of Michigan Symphony Band on its 1961 tour of the Soviet Union and the Near East. The majority of the collection is materials relating to this tour. Other items pertain to historic buildings in Ann Arbor and Camp Michigania
1 linear feet
1 oversize folders UAm
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the material was received in 2007 (donor no. 8542 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Frederick E. Moncrieff was born in Detroit, Michigan, on September 25, 1922, the first child of Frederick Edwin and Kathleen Garnet Moncrieff. After graduating from Southeastern High School in Detroit, he went on to obtain a Bachelor of Arts degree in English from Wayne State University in 1945. Moncrieff worked briefly as a correspondent for the Associated Press in Lansing, Ann Arbor, and Detroit before being hired by the University of Michigan News and Information Services in March 1946, as a photographer. In one of his letters, he mentioned that, "The University purchased my camera and film and even paid me to have the time of my life." Moncrieff added reporter and editor to his responsibilities during his initial ten year stint with the University of Michigan News and Information Services. Among the distinguishing aspects of this period of his career was the organization of the 1955 press conference when Thomas Francis announced that the Salk polio vaccine was safe and effective. He also assisted with the hosting of visiting dignitaries and was the photographer of a famous photograph, taken early in his career, of the University's Diag with students walking amid streaming rays of the sun.
From 1956 to 1958, Moncrieff worked with his mother as a partner and administrator for Cadillac Nursing Homes, Inc., in Detroit, before returning for another eight years with the University of Michigan News and Information Services. After a period as editor of science and engineering news, he was appointed picture editor of the News and Information Services in 1959. Moncrieff was later named coordinator of radio and television news and then, in 1964, became manager of News and Information Services. Among the highlights of this period was his designation as business manager for the University of Michigan Symphony Band tour of Eastern Europe and the Near East from February to June 1961. Aside from handling all of the business affairs for this tour, he also was the press representative and took more than 1000 photos and captured more than 5000 feet of motion picture film during the tour. The UM Band Alumni Organization named Moncrieff as an Honorary Band Alumni in 1964 for the "many ways he has utilized his talents for the service and betterment of the University bands." Moncrieff accepted the position of director of public information at Cleveland State University in 1966, but returned to Ann Arbor three years later to become manager of communication services and educational development at the Commission on Professional and Hospital Activities. He later worked as a realtor and for the advancement department at St. Joseph Mercy Hospital. Moncrieff died March 6, 2008.
__________________________________
Sources:
Moncrieff Obituary The Ann Arbor News, published March 9, 2008
Article The Ann Arbor News, March 13, 2008
Moncrieff Curriculum Vitas (in personal folder)
Moncrieff file, University of Michigan News and Information Services Faculty and Staff files
The Frederick E. Moncrieff papers primarily document Moncrieff's work with the University of Michigan. These papers are divided into three series: University of Michigan Band Tour Papers; Other Materials; and Audiovisual Materials.
Subjects:
Band music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Moncrieff, Frederick E.; Soviet Union--Description and travel.; University of Michigan. News and Information Services.; University of Michigan. Symphony Band.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Bands.; Dwellings--Michigan--Lodi Plains.; Kempf House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Lodi Academy.; Lodi Plains (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Moncrieff, Frederick E.; Wilson-Wahr House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Cavender, George.; Moncrieff, Frederick E.; Munson, Gregory W.; Revelli, William D. (William Donald), 1902-1994.; University of Michigan. Symphony Band.; Sound recordings.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- University of Michigan Band Tour Papers 1960-2000
  The University of Michigan Band Tour Papers, 1960-2000, document Moncrieff's activities regarding the University of Michigan Symphony Band tour of Eastern Europe and the Near East in 1961. Among these materials are correspondence, lists of participants, press releases, newspaper and magazine articles, postcards, a scrapbook, and tourist items (tickets, postcards, guidebooks, etc.). Slides, photographs, and audiotapes relating to the tour are found in the Audiovisual Materials series.
  - Drafts of Articles about the Tour (Box 1)
  - Invitations (Box 1)
  - Itineraries and Log (Box 1)
  - Lists of Tour Personnel (Box 1)
  - News Clippings (Box 1)
  - News Releases (Box 1)
  - Notes and Miscellaneous Letters (Box 1)
  - Official Greetings (Box 1)
  - Personal Letters to his Family (Box 1)
  - Postcards (Box 1)
  - Programs (Box 1)
  - Published Stories (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Box 1)
  - Summary Description of Footage Shot during Tour (Box 1)
  - Tourist Guidebooks (Box 1)
  - Transcript of Interviews during Tour; Congratulatory Notes; Tour Information (Box 1)
  - Travel Tickets and Memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Russia Tour Band Reunions and Correspondence 1981-2000 (Box 1)
  - William Revelli 1971-1994 (Box 1)
- Other Materials 1960-1966
  The Other Materials series, 1960-1966, includes personal papers such as vitas and Moncrieff's passport, and various press releases from the University of Michigan News and Information Services.
  - Assorted News Releases (1961-1963) (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers (1960-1966) (Box 1)
- Audiovisual Materials 1947-circa 1966
  The Audiovisual Materials series, 1947-ca. 1966, includes photographs, slides, and audiotapes of interviews and concerts from the University of Michigan Band Tour. The audiotapes are reel-to-reel recordings of concerts in the Soviet Union broadcast by Radio Moscow as well as post-tour interviews with participants. There are also photographs and a 16 mm color film of Camp Michigania, photographs of historic buildings, campus photographs, including the famous photograph from 1947 showing students on the Diag walking amid streaming rays of the morning sun, and some images of Moncrieff in the Audiovisual Materials series. The campus photographs and some of the Band Tour images are located in the oversize folder.
  - University of Michigan Band Tour
    - Audiotapes of WUOM Broadcast of Concert at Leningrad Conservatory via Radio Moscow, 1/4 inch magnetic tape reel (Box 1)
    - Audiotape of WUOM Broadcast of Concert recorded by Radio Moscow (Box 1)
    - Audiotapes of post-tour interviews with Gregory Munson, Tour Librarian, and with Dr. Revelli and Mr. Cavender, 1/4 inch magnetic tape reels and cassette (Box 1)
    - Audiotape of unknown interview (1/4 inch magnetic tape reel) (Box 1)
    - Photographs of Tour (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Band Tour Photographs (Folder UAm)
    - Slides of Tour (Box 1)
  - Historic Buildings
    - Photographs and Negatives of Ann Arbor Homes (Box 1)
    - Photograph of House formerly used as Lodi Plains Academy (Box 1)
  - Camp Michigania
    - Photographs and Article (Box 1)
    - Motion Picture Film, 16 mm, color, silent, ca. 5 min (Box 1)
  - Portraits
    - Photographs of Moncrieff 1958-1960s (Box 1)
      (see also outsize folder)
  - University of Michigan
    - University of Michigan Campus Photographs (Folder 1)
Related Material
For additional material relating to Moncrieff's work, researchers are encouraged to consult the records of the University of Michigan News and Information Services, including both photographic and press files.
Additional material on the 1961 Symphony Band Tour may be found in the following record groups and collections:
William D. Revelli papers
University of Michigan Band records
Passport to Russia by Josephine Wunsch (a fictionalized account of the University of Michigan Symphony Band 1961 tour of the Soviet Union by one of the student participants.)